Dennis R. Townsend Jr.

1050 Atherton Lane | Woodstock GA. 30189 (770) 990-3994, drtownsendir@gmail.com

Experienced Construction Professional with 25+ years' experience estimating and managing successful projects. Productive team player and leader ensuring on-time and on-budget project completion. I am a strong facilitator, team builder & creative problem solver with a successful track record of fostering lasting business relationships with customers and subcontractors.

Professional Experience

SR. Estimator, IDC Construction

2016-Present

Sr. Estimator responsible for Takeoff and estimating for Renovations of Hotels and Large resorts. Estimator responsibilities included, material takeoff, pricing, preconstruction marketing and subcontractor bid list management as well as managing the team of junior estimators.

Owner/Estimator Townsend Cost Consulting

2015-2016

TCC provides cost estimating for Owners, Architects, Engineers, Contractors and Sub-contractors. TCC can provide services for nearly all building types ranging from Single Family Housing to Commercial Projects. Past experience with Assisted Living Facilities, small University & College buildings, Medical Office Buildings (MOB), office, retail and Industrial Buildings. TCC provides Cost Management services from the project budgeting phase through completion of constructive documents, in addition to preparing cost estimates at each major design phase. TCC utilizes PlanSwift for takeoff and Cost database loaded with the most current RS Means and industry costs for pricing.

Project Manager Estimator, Peacock Builders

2013-2015

Estimator and Project manager responsible for large Assisting Living facilities, Medical offices and dentist offices. Estimator responsibilities included, material takeoff, pricing, preconstruction marketing and subcontractor bid list management. Project Management responsibilities included, specification compliance and quality control, contract administration, applications for payment, review and approval of subcontractor invoices, scheduling and cost control, RFI Management and Submittal Management.,

Pre-construction Manager, Senior Project Manager, Hermosa Construction Group

2013

Pre-Construction Manager/Senior Project manager responsible for all preconstruction, estimating and bidding, project management of a MOB in Augusta, GA. Took over the project as the third PM to manage the project. Estimated as a subcontractor for concrete on Military buildings throughout the southeast. Updated and maintained Timberline estimating system.

Project Manager, GSFIC 2006-2012

Responsible for administration and interface with diverse stakeholders for large capitally funded state construction projects including; Rehabilitation Centers, Residence Halls, University Libraries, Wellness Centers, Classroom Buildings and Site Development. Administered Clients, Contractors, Architects, and Engineers. Coordinated procurement process for DBB,/GC and DP contracts, monitoring and managed budgets, and draw approval process.

Developed into leadership position responsible for mentoring and training new agency project managers. Received Directors Award of Excellence for 2007 completion of the Kia Sitework project. 12 mil CY of soil moved in 9 months

Project Manager, Estimator, Aviation Constructors

2003-2004 and 2005-2006

Lead Estimator/Project manager responsible for all preconstruction and project management of multi-family, higher education and aviation projects. Estimated and successfully managed I-87 Bartow Center. Updated and maintained Timberline estimating system.

Estimator, Atlantic Skanska 2004 - 2005

Estimator responsible for site work and architectural takeoffs, pricing, subcontractor bid list management, bid invitations, HCSS estimating, as well as extensive hand takeoff for hard bid, waste water and light rail maintenance facilities.

Estimator, Project Manager, Kajima Construction Services

1995-2003

Estimator and Project manager responsible for large commercial warehouse, distribution and manufacturing facilities. Estimator responsibilities included, material takeoff, pricing, preconstruction marketing and subcontractor bid list management. Performed cost analysis of past jobs and estimates to improve historical data and improve hit ratio. Project Management responsibilities included, specification compliance and quality control, contract administration, applications for payment, review and approval of subcontractor invoices, scheduling and cost control., Received Safety award for companies only project with zero incidents in 1997. Managed 4,000,000 SF of tilt-up warehouses, averaging a profit of 5% over all the projects. Successful in reducing completion of 136,000 SF shell by 25%.

Educational & Additional Skills

Clemson University, Clemson, South Carolina
Bachelors of Science in Construction Science and Management, 1995
Experienced in Timberline, Plan Swift, On-Screen Takeoff, HCSS,, P3, Suretrak, Microsoft Project, Microsoft
Office